<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: social media | machty's thoughtz]]></title>
  <link href="http://machty.github.com/blog/categories/social-media/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://machty.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-15T10:22:25-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://machty.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Matchneer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Social Media Triggers]]></title>
    <link href="http://machty.github.com/blog/2014/06/29/social-media-triggers/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-29T19:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://machty.github.com/blog/2014/06/29/social-media-triggers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've enjoyed about a week away from Twitter, and hope to prolong this
hiatus. Twitter isn't consistent with a lot of the lifestyle
changes I've been nagging myself to make. Twitter is snack drawer
positioned arms-reach away from the bed of someone trying to maintain a
diet. It's a total trigger for me to retrogress into class clown attention
whore behavior I've been exhibiting since I was 5. So I'm on a break.</p>

<p>Twitter encourages me to project a public facade of empty-headed
buffoonery fueled by zany sarcasm and Photoshop. The last few months,
I've had various opportunities to meet in person people who only know me
by this facade, and it's draining and depressing to keep it up in
person.</p>

<p>So I'm on a break. I've rediscovered distraction-free boredom. And it's
been glorious. I play music again. I sing. When I get frustrated in my
endeavors to improve at my hobbies or my crafts, I have one less
mindless outlet distracting me away from pushing through the difficult
moments. Maybe I'll return to Twitter when I have an album to promote.
Or something worth talking about.</p>

<p>This is where I'm supposed to apologize for a serious post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
