<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: scroll | machty's thoughtz]]></title>
  <link href="http://machty.github.com/blog/categories/scroll/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://machty.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-29T07:48:38-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://machty.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Matchneer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[jQuery Accelerated Hover Scroll]]></title>
    <link href="http://machty.github.com/blog/2012/11/12/jquery-accelerated-hover-scroll/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-12T03:43:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://machty.github.com/blog/2012/11/12/jquery-accelerated-hover-scroll</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Working on a small-ish brochure app for a beach resort, and there's one
section that called for a horizontal scrolling container based on where
the mouse was hovering over the container. The closer you hover to the
edge, the faster the container scrolls. This is by no means a new user
interaction, but I couldn't find a suitable plugin for my needs, so I
wrote one, and you can check it out / download it
<a href="https://github.com/useful-robot/jquery.accel-hover-scroll">here</a>.</p>

<p>I took perhaps 3 separate stabs at this surprisingly awkward problem,
and here's what I learned...</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Debounce!</h3>

<p><a href="http://unscriptable.com/2009/03/20/debouncing-javascript-methods/">Read this article</a>
on debouncing your JavaScript methods.  In particular:</p>

<blockquote><p>Debouncing means to coalesce several temporally close signals into one signal.</p></blockquote>

<p>In the JavaScript/UI/jQuery world, a focus on debouncing has resulted in
some popular solutions to common jank you're probably familiar with.
Here's one:</p>

<p>Don't fire off expensive resize/relayout/repaints every time your
browser window resizes. Most likely, the user is probably still
actively resizing the window, and an expensive relayout/repaint is
just going to jank up a simple browser resize.
<a href="http://paulirish.com/2009/throttled-smartresize-jquery-event-handler/">One solution</a>
is to coalesce all of those resize events into on relayout/repaint,
which is pretty easy to do: just set a timer for a few hundred
milliseconds once a resize event is received, and in that time,
if another resize event is received, reset the timer, and don't do
anything until that timer has elapsed.</p>

<p>So how does this apply to accelerated-hover-scroll?</p>

<h3>mousemove</h3>

<p>I tried a bunch of different approaches to solving the problem of
how to smoothly alter the scroll speed while the container was actively
scrolling. The algorithm I landed on goes like this:</p>

<ul>
<li>Once the user hovers over the the scroll area, ANYWHERE in the
container, start listening for mousemove events.</li>
<li>Once a mousemove event comes in, figure out how close to the edge the
cursor is and decided whether the container should be scrolling at
all, and at what speed.</li>
<li>Now figure out how far the container is from a full scroll either left
or right. If the container's currently scrolled 100 pixels, and it
could scroll 300px total before all the inner content is revealed,
this calculated scrollable distance would be 200px.</li>
<li>Start an animation from the current scroll to to the max possible
scroll using this calculated duration. If you don't move your mouse
again, the container will continue all the way to the and stop when it
gets there. There's no more plugin maintenance to, say, calculate the
pixel amount that the container should scroll for each tick, or
anything messy like that. If the user moves their mouse again, you can
recalculate the new speed based on edge proximity, stop the existing
animation, and start again going all the way to the max scroll, only
at a different duration this time around.</li>
</ul>


<p>A decent solution, but still marred by slowness if the user was moving
their mouse around frequently. If the user was moving their mouse around
over the container while the container was scrolling, all sorts of jank
would happen. And why? Because I wasn't debouncing mousemove. If the
user moved the mouse a single pixel, I'd have halt the animation,
recalculate some things, and start of the animation again with a
negligibly different duration. So how does one debounce a spatial event,
rather than the typical debouncing definition which addresses temporal
events? I used "slices".</p>

<h3>Slices</h3>

<p>If you look at the CoffeeScript source for this plugin, in the
<code>_onMouseMove</code> function, there's a part that calculates the "slice"
that this mouse move falls into. A slice is just a region a few pixels
wide that doesn't show up in any visual sense, but is used to debounce a
spatial mousemove event. Basically, if we've already started animating
the container and a mousemove event is received that is just a few
pixels away, we can very simply calculate that the mouseevent falls into
the same slice as the original mouse event that launched the animation,
and discard the newer event rather than slow everything down so that we can
have a pixel perfect scroll velocity mapping.</p>

<p>So, whether or not I'm butchering the term "debounce" by applying it to
spatial events, the lesson is the same, which is that you should avoid
pixel-perfect/millisecond-perfect granularity if at all possible. Most
likely no one will notice the downgrade in strict continuity, but they
will notice if a bunch of frequent, redundant, complicated
redraws/relayouts/repaints fire off for every little insignificant
event.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
